Guide to the New-York Historical Society Original Building Planning & Construction Records 1848-1946 NYHS-RG 3
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Andrew J. Robinson Company.; New-York Historical Society. -- Archives; New-York Historical Society. -- Buildings; Turner Construction Company.; Walker & Gillette.; York & Sawyer.; Architectural firms -- New York (State) -- New York; Architectural records; Central Park (New York, N.Y.); Central Park West (New York, N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Contracts; Correspondence; Invoices; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York -- Designs and plans; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York -- Drawings; Libraries and institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Designs and plans; Libraries and institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Drawings; Minute books; Museum buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Designs and plans; Museum buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Drawings; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Specifications; Subscription lists
- Series I. 2nd Avenue Building, 1848-1860, 1906-1912; 1.23 Linear feet in 2 document boxes and 3 oversize folders
  Arrangement Note
  The series is arranged by format, beginning with minute books and other documents related to the overall activities of the building committees. These are followed by other formats, such as subscription books, that relate to particular aspects of the project. These formats proceed in a rough chronological order.
  Scope and Contents Note
  The 2nd Avenue Building series includes documents concerning N-YHS's initiative in the mid-nineteenth century to construct a fireproof building to house and to present its collections. The series includes the minute books for three of the committees involved with the project: the committee to raise funds for the project, the trustees of the Building Fund, and the Building Committee charged by the trustees with responsibility for land acquisition and building design and construction. The series includes the printed specifications for the project, estimates received from contractors for the various aspects of the construction, contracts with some of the contractors, and summaries of the project revenue and expenses. There are several subscription books from both the original drive for funds in the late 1840s-early 1850s, and the drive for additional funds in 1856.
  The correspondence includes several letters from the project's architects, Mettam & Burke, as well as from the various craftsmen bidding for work or responding to changes in the project's original specifications. The correspondence also includes a few offers to N-YHS for real estate in 1850-1851, and documents concerning N-YHS's eventual sale of the building in the early twentieth century.
  The series holds about 25 architectural drawings, including floor plans, elevations, transverse views, longitudinal views, and others. Some of these are dated as from 1854 and are stamped or signed as the work product of architects (George B.) Carstesen & (C.H.) Gildemeister; these are likely the proposals that were ultimately not accepted by N-YHS. The other drawings in the series are undated and unsigned.
  Access Restrictions
  An appointment is required for access to the architectural drawings in this series. Please contact the Print Room at printroom@nyhistory.org.
  - Minutes. Building Committee and Committee on Subscriptions to the Building Fund, 1848-1857 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    The book includes the minutes for Building Committee meetings from February 22, 1848, to December 9, 1851, and the minutes for the Committee on Subscriptions to the Building Fund meetings from January 26, 1852, to its final meeting on February 2, 1857, with its final report of February 3, 1857, written by Chairman Luther Bradish. Loose sheets found in the book were separated to the following folder.
  - Loose Documents Removed from Minutes, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes two sheets, including a list of individuals associated with an unnamed committee.
  - Minutes. Committee, or Trustees, of the Building Fund., 1848-1855 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    The minutes book includes a copy of the appeal of October 30, 1848, for funds for a fireproof building, with the trustees' meeting minutes from January 29, 1850, to June 2, 1855. Loose sheets found in the book were separated to the following folder.
  - Loose Documents Removed from Minutes, 1855-1857 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes lists of trustees, trustee donations, a copy of the 1856 appeal for building donations, draft minutes of the January 31, 1855, meeting, and some Building Fund financial records (1855-57).
  - Minutes. Building Committee, 1850, 1853-1857 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    The minutes book includes an opening note recounting the authorization of the committee from its creation on January 29, 1850, to the beginning of its minutes in this book on December 9, 1853. The note states that proceedings for pre-1853 meetings are recorded in the reports of the committee found in the minutes book of the Trustees of the Building Fund (see above). The minutes end on May 9, 1857, though later dated loose sheets found in the book were separated to the following folder.
  - Loose Documents Removed from Minutes, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes notes from committee meetings held in May and June 1857, and a letter from Andrew Warner to B.R. Winthrop of September 29, 1857, commenting on the construction and financial matters.
  - Committee Reports, Drafts, Notes (1 of 4), 1850-1854, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes two reports from 1850 regarding the effort to raise subscriptions for the proposed building and one report from 1850 regarding N-YHS and the New York Society Library's consideration of jointly purchasing and occupying a site, with the results of their review of available properties. Includes notes and correspondence (1853-1854) concerning meetings of the Buildings Committee and negotiations with neighboring Tabernacle Baptist Church for acquisition of a strip of land. Includes miscellaneous subscription materials (circa 1854).
  - Committee Reports, Drafts, Notes (2 of 4), 1855-1858, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes notes or draft minutes of building trustee meetings, with financial data and reports from the trustees' Buildings Committee.
  - Committee Reports, Drafts, Notes (3 of 4), 1853, 1860, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes draft reports of the Buildings Committee and the Subscription Committee; Luther Bradish's remarks at the dedication of the building; an admission ticket to the dedication; financial and other notes, at least some of which were supplied to Bradish by Librarian George Moore; and an agreement for mason work on 4th Avenue to which N-YHS was not a party (this is possibly a form of agreement referenced by Bradish).
  - Committee Reports, Drafts, Notes (4 of 4), undated (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 4)
    Includes one oversize pencil drawing on tracing paper of a building. The drawing is undated and unattributed and was found with the Building Committee reports. It does not appear to be the N-YHS building as built.
  - Subscription Books (4), circa 1848 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subscription Book (1), 1850-1851 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes one booklet and loose sheets (correspondence and a subscriber list) from the booklet.
  - Subscription Books (2), 1856-1857 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Appears to be two summary lists of subscribers from 1848-1854.
  - Subscription Books (5) (1 of 2), 1856-1857 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    This folder and the next include booklets recording subscriptions for the 1856 appeal to complete the building, especially the galleries for art.
  - Subscription Books (1) (2 of 2), 1856-1857 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Building Fund Lecture Admission Ticket, 1852-1853 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Offers of Property, 1850-1851, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Offers from Francis B. Cutting (Lafayette Place), Samuel B. Ruggles (4th Ave between 17th and 18th), and Edward Ludlow (5th Ave between 17th and 18th).
  - Architectural Drawings (1 of 2), 1854, undated (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 2)
    This folder and the next include presentation drawings for the 2nd Avenue building, including floor plans, elevations, interior and exterior views, and longitudinal and transverse views. Several of the drawings are signed or stamped as created by Carstensen & Gildemeister. An appointment is required for access to these architectural drawings. Please contact the Print Room at printroom@nyhistory.org.
  - Architectural Drawings (2 of 2), 1854, undated (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 3)
  - Specifications, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes the printed specifications from architects Mettam & Burke for: carpenter's work, iron work, marble work, mason's work, and stone work. The folder also includes the mason and carpenter specifications for the New York Society Library to be built in University Place.
  - Correspondence (1 of 3), 1854-1857 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    This folder and the next two include correspondence with estimates from contractors, a progress report (December 1856) and other correspondence from architects Mettam & Burke, and other documents related to work on the building.
  - Correspondence (2 of 3), 1855-1857 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (3 of 3), 1855-1857 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Contracts (1 of 2), 1855-1856 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes contracts with J.B. and W.W. Cornell (iron work) and Masterton, Smith, and Sinclair (stonecutting).
  - Contracts (2 of 2), 1855-1856 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes contracts with Benjamin F. Camp (mason work and coal vault) and draft contract with John Galier (carpenter).
  - Financial (1 of 2), 1857 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    This folder and the next hold records related to the costs of the building project. This first folder holds records concerning the history of payments over the course of the project and notes on contracted payments, extras, and other financial matters. The next folder holds some bills and some miscellaneous notes about subscriptions.
  - Financial (2 of 2), 1856-1858 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Designs for Lamps, Undated (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 23)
    General Note
    Includes six undated and unattributed designs for what appear to be table top reading lamps. It is believed that these designs relate to N-YHS's 2nd Avenue building, though there is no clear basis for that. A notation with the drawings indicates that they were a gift of Phyllis Lucas of the Old Print Gallery in 1976.
  - Offers for 2nd Avenue Building, 1906-1907 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Sale of 2nd Avenue Building, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series II. Proposed Central Park Building, 1860-1876; 0.58 Linear feet in one bound volume, one document box, and one oversize folder
  The series opens with the minutes of the Building Committee (1863-67). The remainder of the series is arranged in rough chronological order. Some documents, though out of strict chronological order, were kept together as found because they were all supporting documents used at particular N-YHS or Executive Committee meetings; these are in order of meeting date. Also, documents were kept together regardless of sequence when it appeared they had been originally filed together.
  The series includes a rich set of material documenting N-YHS's eventually unsuccessful attempt to establish a Museum of Antiquities, Science, and Art on the site of the Arsenal in Central Park. The series includes the minutes of the Building Committee formed in 1863 to pursue the Central Park initiative. The minutes, which run until January 1867, have introductory entries transcribing earlier related documents, beginning August 14, 1860. Other documents include correspondence between N-YHS committee members, such as Luther Bradish, George Moore, and Charles Kirkland, and between N-YHS and the Board of Commissioners of Central Park, including Comptroller Andrew H. Green. There is one letter each from Frederick Law Olmsted and J.J. Jarves. Other documents include N-YHS resolutions, committee reports, copies of N-YHS's memorials to the New York State legislature, the 1862 legislative bill authorizing the Commissioners to set apart the Arsenal for N-YHS, and others. There are various summaries of the progress of events over the years, some in draft form, including an 1876 summary written by Edward de Lancey. The series includes one oversize 1865 advertisement for real estate and stock auctioneers Adrian H. Muller, P.R. Wilkins & Co.; the advertisement is in the form of a pictorial map of Central Park with surrounding lots.
  - Minutes of the Building Committee, 1863 June 9-1867 January 25 (Volume RG3.1, Folder -)
  - Central Park Matter, 1860-1862 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Central Park Matter, 1862-1863 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Central Park Matter, 1863-1864 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Central Park Matter, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Central Park Matter (1 of 2), 1863-1866 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes a October 22, 1864, letter from J.J. Jarves to Frederic De Peyster regarding the size of various major European museums. The folder includes a portion of the original envelope that held some of these documents; an annotation on that envelope indicates that the documents were presented to N-YHS by Gen. J. Watts DePeyster on Dec. 17, 1907.
  - Central Park Matter (2 of 2), 1865 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 21)
    Includes one oversize 1865 advertisement removed from the above folder. The ad is for real estate and stock auctioneers Adrian H. Muller, P.R. Wilkins & Co. and is in the form of a pictorial map of Central Park with surrounding lots.
  - Central Park Matter, 1865-1866 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Central Park Matter, 1866-1867 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Central Park Matter, 1868 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Central Park Matter, 1871-1872 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Includes a letter of October 3, 1872, from Frederick Law Olmsted to R. Martin proposing a meeting to discuss the N-YHS matter.
  - Central Park Matter, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Central Park Matter, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series III. Central Park West Construction: Central Portion, 1880-1918; 14.43 Linear feet in 7 document boxes, one artifact box, 23 oversize folders, and one roll of drawings
  The series is arranged roughly by format and subject matter. The series opens with the earliest material, the subscription books and appeals of the late 1800s, leading to materials related to the purchase of the Central Park West property in 1891. The series then continues with financial matters related to the development of the Building Fund in the early 1900s, banking records of the Fund, and the expenditures from the Fund for construction and other property-related purposes through 1909. The series then presents the minutes and other general documentation related to the Building Committee, the Trustees of the New Building, and Henry Dexter's donation and involvement with the project. The series closes with materials related to York & Sawyer and other contractor and construction matters, including architectural and other drawings.
  Most of the drawings in the series are standalone documents, no longer directly connected with any underlying contextual material (e.g., transmittal letters) that might have accompanied them originally; any oversize drawings found with such context are referred to at that point in the container list, though the oversize drawing itself was flattened and moved to an appropriate container.
  The series includes a wide range of materials documenting N-YHS's acquisition in 1891 of its current Central Park West site and the construction in the first decade of the twentieth century of the central portion of the building. These documents include financial records, such as the various appeals over decades for funds, subscription books, Building Fund checkbooks and cancelled checks, and contractor invoices and other payments made from the Fund. These financial records also include the arrangements made with Henry Dexter in connection with his donations in support of the construction project. The 1891 purchase of the Central Park West property is documented primarily by the title abstracts, the related official title searches, and the deeds to the purchased lots as compiled and bound by N-YHS's attorney, Weekes Brothers.
  There is also much other material related to the design and construction of the building, in addition to that found in the financial records. These include minutes and correspondence of the N-YHS committees and officers leading the project, correspondence with architects York & Sawyer and others, architectural and other drawings, contracts, and bids and estimates. The bulk of the drawings are by York & Sawyer; others are by civil engineer Peter E. Nostrand and the Library Bureau (library and museum furniture). A small number of post-construction plans, from the 1910s, by the Library Bureau and by the firms of Nygren, Tenney & Ohmes (heating & ventilating) and Snead & Co. (ironwork) are included in the series.
  There is material related to the cornerstone ceremony of November 1903, including artifacts such as pins and ribbons, a small album of photographs, York & Sawyer's plan for the grandstand, and related correspondence.
  - Subscription Books (2), 1880-1881 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Subscription Books (3), 1885-1886 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    One of the three booklets appears to have been used to keep the meeting minutes, or at least some form of the minutes, for the Committee on Subscriptions for a New Building from May 12, 1885, to January 23, 1886.
  - Subscription Books (6), 1887-1888 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Subscription Book (1), 1886-1891 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    The folder includes loose notes and correspondence related to subscriptions found in the booklet.
  - Subscription Lists, 1885-1891 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Includes the 1885 appeal and responses, and includes lists of subscribers with entries to 1891.
  - Subscription Appeal and Responses (1 of 6), 1888 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Includes various printed appeals for subscriptions and payment.
  - Subscription Appeal and Responses (2 of 6), 1888 May-June (Box 4, Folder 7)
    This folder and the next include the commitments received in response to the 1888 appeal for subscriptions.
  - Subscription Appeal and Responses (3 of 6), 1888 May-June (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Subscription Appeal and Responses (4 of 6), 1888 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Includes lists of subscribers.
  - Subscription Appeal and Responses (5 of 6), 1888 October-November (Box 4, Folder 10)
    This folder and the next include the responses to the appeal for payment of the committed subscriptions.
  - Subscription Appeal and Responses (6 of 6), 1888 November-December (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Committee on Subscriptions (1 of 2). Minutes, 1885-1888 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Committee on Subscriptions (2 of 2). Correspondence, 1886-1888 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Certifications, 1888 November 28 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Includes duplicates of two certifications made by the president and treasurer of N-YHS in connection with the Building Fund: that sufficient subscriptions were raised to satisfy the conditions of an 1885 trust deed made to the Central Trust Company of New York, and that N-YHS received from Central Trust the proceeds of the trust.
  - Property & Construction Offers (1 of 3), 1881, 1885, 1888 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence from real estate agents, contractors, and others related to N-YHS's interest in acquiring property during this period.
  - Property & Construction Offers (2 of 3), 1889 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Property & Construction Offers (3 of 3), 1890-1891, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Committee Recommendation for Purchase of the Central Park West Site, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence Concerning Closings, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Abstract of the Title of N-YHS to Ten Lots of Land in the City of New York, 1891 August 19 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Includes the abstract of title and the related official title searches for the Central Park West property prepared and bound by N-YHS's attorneys, Weekes Brothers. Included in the bound documents are the deeds/indentures conveying the purchased lots to N-YHS. Also included is the attorneys' memorandum of charges and disbursements in the matter.
  - Abstract of the Title of N-YHS to Ten Lots of Land in the City of New York (photocopy), 1891 August 19 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    This is a modern photocopy of the original document, except that the attorney's cover letter is not included.
  - Declaration of Uses of Property, Recorded with New York County, 1891 December 6 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Clark Estate Property Matter, 1901-1902 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Easement on West 76th Street Lot, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Includes one letter from Oscar Straus to N-YHS concerning an easement granted to N-YHS in 1891.
  - Property Tax Remission Matter (1 of 2), 1903 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Property Tax Remission Matter (2 of 2), 1903 (Box OS-1, Folder 1)
    Includes a copy of "Notice of sale of lands and tenements within that part of the City of New York known as the borough of Manhattan, for unpaid taxes for the years 1886, 1887, 1888, 1889, 1890, 1891, 1892, 1893, 1894, 1895, 1896, and 1897, also for unpaid Croton water rents for the years...: The Aldermanic Chamber in the City Hall, Borough of Manhattan, City of New York, on Wednesday, September 2, 1903, at 10 o’clock in the forenoon / William E. McFaddin, collector of assessments and arrears of the City of New York. New York, 1903." The reference to N-YHS's unpaid amounts is found on page 29.
  - Committee of Fifteen, 1891-1893 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence, lists, and the 1892 appeal for $1 million to construct a new building on the Central Park West site.
  - Circulars and Appeals for Funds for New Building Construction, 1901-1902 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Building Fund Subscription Committee Minutes, 1901-1903 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Building Fund Subscription Appeal Responses, 1901-1905 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Building Fund Bank Books and Cancelled Checks (1 of 2), 1891-1909 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    This folder and the next includes the passbooks, check books with stubs, and the returned checks, numbered 1-139, for expenses paid out of the Building Fund held at Central Trust Co. of New York. The stubs include descriptive transaction information. The folder also includes a booklet summarizing subscriptions into the Fund and expenses paid out through 1902. See the following set of folders for the invoices, etc. supporting the payments.
  - Building Fund Bank Books and Cancelled Checks (2 of 2), 1891-1909 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Building Fund Expenditures (1 of 8). Payments #13-52, 1894-1904 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    This folder and the next seven include the invoices and other supporting documents for payments from the Building Fund. The documents are in sequence of payments made as noted on the reverse of the documents; the sequence number corresponds with the cancelled check number from the Central Trust account (see above folders). Some payments have multiple supporting documents; the payment number is generally noted on only one of the sheets. There are no documents for payments 1-12 and 138-139; see the checkstubs and cancelled checks for those transactions.
  - Building Fund Expenditures (2 of 8). Payments #53-58, 1905 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Building Fund Expenditures (3 of 8). Payments #59-64, 1905 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Building Fund Expenditures (4 of 8). Payments #65-70, 1906 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Building Fund Expenditures (5 of 8). Payments #71-74, 1906 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Building Fund Expenditures (6 of 8). Payments #75-82, 1906 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Building Fund Expenditures (7 of 8). Payments #83-120, 1907-1908 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Building Fund Expenditures (8 of 8). Payments #121-137, 1908-1909 (Box 6, Folder 12)